So, we used to solve big problems.
وبالتالي , لقد اعتدنا على حل المشاكل الكبيرة .
On July 21st, 1969,
في 21 يوليو, 1969,
Buzz Aldrin climbed out of Apollo 11's lunar module
صعد باز الدرين من وحدة أبولو 11 على سطح القمر
and descended onto the Sea of Tranquility.
و هبط على بحر ترانكوليتي
Armstrong and Aldrin were alone,
كان ارمسترونغ والدرين لوحدهما،
but their presence on the moon's gray surface
لكن وجودهم على سطح القمر الرمادي
was the culmination of a convulsive, collective effort.
كان تتويجا للتماسك والجهد الجماعي.
The Apollo program was the greatest
كان برنامج أبولو الاكبر
peacetime mobilization
في تجنيد زمن السلم
in the history of the United States.
في تاريخ الولايات المتحدة .
To get to the moon, NASA spent
انفقت ناسا للصعود للقمر
around 180 billion dollars in today's money,
ما يقارب 180مليون دولار في سعرعملة اليوم ,
or four percent of the federal budget.
او اربعة بالمئة من ميزانية الاتحاد الفدرالي.
Apollo employed around 400,000 people
وظف أبولو ما يقارب 400.000 شخص
and demanded the collaboration of 20,000
و قد طالب بالتعاون مع 20،000
companies, universities and government agencies.
من شركات و جامعات و جهات حكومية .
People died, including the crew of Apollo 1.
لقد توفي اشخاص , شمل ذلك طاقم أبولو 1.
But before the Apollo program ended,
لكن قبل نهاية برنامج أبولو ,
24 men flew to the moon.
24 رجل صعد للقمر .
Twelve walked on its surface, of whom Aldrin,
مشى احدى عشر شخص على سطح القمر , كان من بينهم الدرين,
following the death of Armstrong last year,
تبع ذلك وفاة ارمسترونغ السنة الماضية ,
is now the most senior.
و هو الحدث الاكبر الان .
So why did they go?
لكن لماذا ذهبوا ؟
They didn't bring much back:
لم يحضروا الكثير معهم :
841 pounds of old rocks,
841 رطل من الحجارة القديمة ,
and something all 24 later emphasized --
و شيء كل 24 أكد في وقت لاحق -
a new sense of the smallness
و ادراك جديد للصغر
and the fragility of our common home.
وهشاشة الوطن المعروف.
Why did they go? The cynical answer is they went
لماذا ذهبوا ؟ الجواب الساخر انهم ذهبوا
because President Kennedy wanted to show
لأن الرئيس كنيدي اراد ان يثبت لـ
the Soviets that his nation had the better rockets.
السوفييت أن هذه الأمة لديها صواريخ أفضل.
But Kennedy's own words at Rice University in 1962
ولكن الكلمة التي القاها كنيدي في جامعة رايس في عام 1962
provide a better clue.
تقديم فكرة أفضل.
(Video) John F. Kennedy: But why, some say, the moon?
يقول البعض،ولكن لماذا , القمر ؟
Why choose this as our goal?
لماذا تم اختيار هذا كهدف لنا ؟
And they may well ask,
وقد يتساءلون،
why climb the highest mountain?
لماذا تسلقوا أعلى قمة جبلية؟
Why, 35 years ago, fly the Atlantic?
لماذا، قبل 35 عاما، حلقو الى المحيط الأطلسي؟
Why does Rice play Texas?
لماذا رايس تلعب تكساس؟
We choose to go to the moon.
لقد اخترنا الذهاب الى القمر .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We choose to go to the moon in this decade,
لقد اخترنا الذهاب الى القمر في هذا العقد ,
and do the other things,
وفعل أشياء أخرى،,
not because they are easy, but because they are hard.
ليس لأنها سهلة، ولكن لأنها صعبة.
Jason Pontin: To contemporaries,
بالنسبة إلى معاصريه،
Apollo wasn't only a victory of West over East
كان أبولو ليس فقط انتصارا للغرب أو الشرق
in the Cold War.
في الحرب الباردة .
At the time, the strongest emotion
في وقت , المشاعر الاقوى
was of wonder
كانت الدهشة
at the transcendent powers of technology.
في تعالي قوى التكنولوجيا .
They went because it was a big thing to do.
لقد ذهبوا لانه كان شيء كبير ليقوموا به .
Landing on the moon occurred in the context
ظهرالهبوط على القمر في سياق
of a long series of technological triumphs.
سلسلة طويلة من الانتصارات التكنولوجية.
The first half of the 20th century produced
أنتج النصف الأول من القرن 20
the assembly line and the airplane,
خط التجميع والطائرة
penicillin and a vaccine for tuberculosis.
و البنسلين ولقاح لمرض السل.
In the middle years of the century,
في منتصف سنوات القرن،
polio was eradicated and smallpox eliminated.
لقد تم القضاء على شلل الأطفال و القضاء على الجدري.
Technology itself seemed to possess
بدت التكنولوجيا في حد ذاتها مسيطرة
what Alvin Toffler in 1970
ما هو ألفين توفلر في عام 1970
called "accelerative thrust."
الذي يدعى "الدفعةِ التعجيليةِ "
For most of human history,
بالنسبة لمعظم التاريخ البشري،
we could go no faster than a horse
لا يمكن أن نسير أسرع من الحصان
or a boat with a sail,
أو قارب مع الشراع،
but in 1969, the crew of Apollo 10
لكن في عام 1969،طاقم أبولو 10
flew at 25,000 miles an hour.
حلق بسرعة 25،000 ميل في الساعة.
Since 1970, no human beings
منذ عام 1970،ما من بشر
have been back to the moon.
كان قد عاد إلى القمر.
No one has traveled faster than the crew
و ما من أحد سافر أسرع من الطاقم
of Apollo 10,
أبولو 10،
and blithe optimism about technology's powers
والتفاؤل المفرح حول صلاحيات التكنولوجيا
has evaporated
قد تبخر
as big problems we had imagined technology would solve,
كما قد تصورنا أن التكنولوجيا ستحل مشاكل كبيرة ،
such as going to Mars,
كالذهاب الى المريخ ,
creating clean energy, curing cancer,
خلق الطاقة النظيفة، وعلاج السرطان،
or feeding the world have come to seem
أو إطعام العالم قد بدا
intractably hard.
مستعصي الحل.
I remember watching the liftoff of Apollo 17.
أتذكر مشاهدة اقلاع أبولو 17.
I was five years old,
لقد كنت خمس سنوات ,
and my mother told me not to stare
وقد قالت لي والدتي ان لا احدق
at the fiery exhaust of a Saturn V rocket.
في العادم الناري لصاروخ v زحل.
I vaguely knew this was to be the last
كنت اعرف بشكل غامض أن هذا كان ليكون الاخير
of the moon missions,
من بعثات القمر،
but I was absolutely certain there would be
لكنني كنت واثق تماما انه سيكون هناك
Mars colonies in my lifetime.
مستعمرات مريخ في حياتي.
So "Something happened
لذلك "حدث شيء
to our capacity to solve big problems with technology"
لقدرتنا في حل مشاكل كبيرة باستخدام التكنولوجيا "
has become a commonplace.
أصبح شائعا.
You hear it all the time.
ستسمعه في كل وقت.
We've heard it over the last two days here at TED.
لقد سمعناه على مدى اليومين الماضيين هنا في TED.
It feels as if technologists have diverted us
انه يشعر كما لوان التكنولوجيين حولتنا
and enriched themselves with trivial toys,
واثروا أنفسهم بالالعاب التافهة،
with things like iPhones and apps and social media,
بأشياء مثل أجهزة iPhone وتطبيقات وسائل الاتصال الاجتماعية،
or algorithms that speed automated trading.
أو الخوارزميات سريعة التداول الآلي.
There's nothing wrong with most of these things.
لا يوجد شيء خاطئ مع معظم هذه الأشياء.
They've expanded and enriched our lives.
لقد توسعت واثرت حياتنا.
But they don't solve humanity's big problems.
لكنها لا تحل مشاكل الإنسانية الكبرى.
What happened?
ماذا حدث ؟
So there is a parochial explanation in Silicon Valley,
حتى لا يكون هناك تفسير ضيق في سيليكون فالي،
which admits that it has been funding less ambitious companies
الذي يعترف أنه قد تم تمويل شركات أقل طموحا
than it did in the years when it financed
مما كان عليه في السنوات عندما قاموا بتمويل
Intel, Microsoft, Apple and Genentech.
إنتل، ومايكروسوفت، وأبل وجينينتيك.
Silicon Valley says the markets are to blame,
وتقول فالي سليكون ان الاسواق هي السبب ,
in particular the incentives that venture capitalists
ولا سيما الحوافز التي أصحاب رؤوس الأموال
offer to entrepreneurs.
يقدموها لأصحاب المشاريع.
Silicon Valley says that venture investing
وتقول فالي سيليكون ان مشروع الاستثمار
shifted away from funding transformational ideas
تحول بعيدا عن تمويل الأفكار المنتقلة
and towards funding incremental problems
والى تمويل مشاكل الإضافية
or even fake problems.
او حتى مشاكل مزيفة .
But I don't think that explanation is good enough.
لكن لا اعتقد ان هذا الشرح جيد بما فيه الكفاية .
It mostly explains what's wrong with Silicon Valley.
وهذا في الغالب ما يفسر الخطأ في وادي السليكون.
Even when venture capitalists were at their most
حتى عندما كان معظم أصحاب رؤوس الأموال الخاصة بهم في
risk-happy, they preferred small investments,
المخاطر - بسعاده، انهم يفضلون الاستثمارات الصغيرة،
tiny investments that offered an exit within 10 years.
الاستثمارات الصغيرة التي عرضت للخروج في غضون 10 سنوات.
V.C.s have always struggled
V.C.s كافحت دائما
to invest profitably in technologies such as energy
للاستثمار المربح في مجال تكنولوجيات مثل الطاقة
whose capital requirements are huge
التي متطلبات رأس مالها ضخمة
and whose development is long and lengthy,
والتي تنميها طويلة ومطولة،
and V.C.s have never, never funded the development
و ابداV.C.s لم تقم , ابدا بتمويل التطور
of technologies meant to solve big problems
في مجال التكنولوجيا المعني بحل المشاكل الكبيرة
that possess no immediate commercial value.
التي لا تملك قيمة تجارية فورية.
No, the reasons we can't solve big problems
لا، أسباب أننا لا نستطيع أن نحل المشاكل الكبيرة
are more complicated and more profound.
هو أكثر تعقيدا وأكثر عمقا.
Sometimes we choose not to solve big problems.
أحيانا نختار عدم حل المشاكل الكبيرة.
We could go to Mars if we want.
يمكن أن نذهب إلى المريخ إذا أردنا.
NASA even has the outline of a plan.
حتى ان ناسا لديها الخطوط العريضة للخطة.
But going to Mars would follow a political decision
لكن الذهاب الى المريخ سيتبع قرار سياسي
with popular appeal, and that will never happen.
مع نداء شعبية، وهذا لن يحدث أبدا.
We won't go to Mars, because everyone thinks
ونحن لن نذهب إلى المريخ، لأن الجميع يفكر في ذلك
there are more important things
هناك اشياء اكثر اهمية
to do here on Earth.
لنقوم بها هنا على كوكب الارض .
Sometimes, we can't solve big problems
احيانا , لا يمكننا حل المشاكل الكبيرة
because our political systems fail.
لأن أنظمتنا السياسية تفشل.
Today, less than two percent
اليوم، أقل من اثنين في المئة
of the world's energy consumption
من استهلاك الطاقة في العالم
derives from advanced, renewable sources
تستمد من مصادر متقدمة و متجددة
such as solar, wind and biofuels,
مثل الطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح والوقود الحيوي،
less than two percent,
أقل من اثنين في المئة،
and the reason is purely economic.
والسبب هو اقتصادي بحت.
Coal and natural gas are cheaper
الفحم والغاز الطبيعي أرخص
than solar and wind,
من الطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح،
and petroleum is cheaper than biofuels.
والبترول أرخص من الوقود الحيوي.
We want alternative energy sources
نريد مصادر الطاقة البديلة
that can compete on price. None exist.
التي بامكانها أن تتنافس على السعر. لا يوجد أي منها.
Now, technologists, business leaders
الآن والتكنولوجيين ورجال الأعمال
and economists all basically agree
و الاقتصاديون جميعهم وافقوا جوهريا
on what national policies and international treaties
على ما السياسات الوطنية والمعاهدات الدولية
would spur the development of alternative energy:
قد تحفز تطور الطاقة البديلة:
mostly, a significant increase in energy
في المقام الأول, زيادة كبيرة في الطاقة و
research and development,
البحث و التطوير
and some kind of price on carbon.
و بعض الانواع من سعر الكربون.
But there's no hope in the present political climate
ولكن ليس هناك أمل في ظل المناخ السياسي الحالي
that we will see U.S. energy policy
ذلك بأننا سوف نرى سياسة الطاقة في الولايات المتحدة
or international treaties that reflect that consensus.
أو المعاهدات الدولية التي تعكس هذا التوافق في الآراء.
Sometimes, big problems that had seemed technological
في بعض الاحيان , المشاكل الكبيرة التي كانت تبدو تكنولوجية
turn out not to be so.
تتحول حتى لا تكون كذلك.
Famines were long understood to be caused
كانت المجاعات و لمدة طويلة مفهومة بانها تحدث
by failures in food supply.
من الاخفاقات في الإمدادات الغذائية.
But 30 years of research have taught us
لكن 30 عام من البحوث قد علمتنا
that famines are political crises
أن المجاعات هي الأزمات السياسية
that catastrophically affect food distribution.
التي تؤثر على نحو خطير في توزيع الطعام.
Technology can improve things like crop yields
تستطيع التكنولوجيا ان تطور الاشياء مثل غلة المحاصيل
or systems for storing and transporting food,
او انظمة لتخزين و نقل الطعام ,
but there will be famines so long as there are bad governments.
لكن سوف يكون هناك مجاعات ما دام هناك حكومات سيئة .
Finally, big problems sometimes elude solution
بالنهاية , المشاكل الكبيرة احيانا مستعصية الحل
because we don't really understand the problem.
لأننا لا نفهم حقا ما مشكلة.
President Nixon declared war on cancer in 1971,
أعلن الرئيس نيكسون الحرب على السرطان في عام 1971،
but we soon discovered
لكننا سرعان ما اكتشفنا
there are many kinds of cancer,
ان هناك انواع عديدة من السرطان ,
most of them fiendishly resistant to therapy,
معظمها مقاومة للعلاج بوحشية،
and it is only in the last 10 years
وأن ليس سوى في السنوات ال 10 الماضية
that effective, viable therapies
علاجات فعالة و مجدية
have come to seem real.
قد اصبحت تبدو حقيقة .
Hard problems are hard.
المشاكل الصعبة صعبة
It's not true that we can't solve big problems through technology.
ليس من الصحيح باننا لا نستطيع حل المشاكل الكبيرة من خلال التكنولوجيا .
We can, we must, but these four elements
نحن نستطيع, بل يجب , لكن هذه الاربع عناصر
must all be present:
يجب جميعها ان تكون موجودة :
Political leaders and the public
القادة السياسيين والجمهور
must care to solve a problem;
ويجب الحرص على حل المشكلة؛
institutions must support its solution;
ويجب على المنظمات ان تدعم حلولها؛
It must really be a technological problem;
يجب أن يكون حقا مشكلة التكنولوجية؛
and we must understand it.
ويجب علينا فهمها
The Apollo mission,
بعثة أبولو،
which has become a kind of metaphor
التي اصبحت نوعا من نوع من الاستعارة
for technology's capacity to solve big problems,
لفدرة التكنولجيا على حل المشاكل الكبيرة ,
met these criteria.
وفق تلك المعايل .
But it is an irreproducible model for the future.
بل هو نموذج غير منتج في المستقبل
It is not 1961.
انها ليست 1961.
There is no galvanizing contest like the Cold War,
ليس هناك مسابقة تعبئة مثل الحرب الباردة،
no politician like John Kennedy
ولا سياسي كجزن كندي
who can heroize the difficult and the dangerous,
الذين يمكن أن بطل االصعوبة والخطروة،
and no popular science fictional mythology
وعدم شعبية علم الخيال العلمي الميثولوجيا
such as exploring the solar system.
مثل استكشاف النظام الشمسي.
Most of all, going to the moon
الأهم من ذلك كله، لذهاب إلى القمر
turned out to be easy.
تحولت لتكون سهلة.
It was just three days away.
لقد كانت فقط ثلاثة ايام بعيدا .
And arguably it wasn't even solving
ويمكن القول أنه لم يكن حتى حل
much of a problem.
للكثير من المشاكل
We are left alone with our day,
تركنا وحيدين مع عصرنا ,
and the solutions of the future will be harder won.
و الحلول للمستقبل سوف تكون صعبة الحصول .
God knows, we don't lack for the challenges.
الله يعلم , ، نحن لا نفتقر لمواجهة التحديات.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)